in this Baldur's Gate 3 fighter class
guide I'm going to be covering the
fighter class including all three
subclasses and providing you some useful
information I'll be doing more build
guides for Baldur's Gate 3 in the
fighter but for now let's just look at
how a fighter functions and its basics
Fighters are the backbone of your front
line and are some of the most capable
Warriors in bg3 not only are they
proficient with all forms of armor but
also all forms of weapons and Shields
and they can heal themselves once per
short rest with their second win class
feature excelling in all forms of
Martial combat Fighters have the
potential to attack more than any other
class in the game on a single turn
this is due to their extra attacks
gained at both levels 5 and 11 as well
as action surge
action surge allows them to take a
second action on a given turn once per
short rest or once per combat
essentially this action can then be used
to trigger their extra attacks all over
again granting them the potential of a
total of six attacks in one turn at
level 11. if they've used this class
feature
in this section we'll take a look at how
to set up your fighter during character
creation for best results we'll begin
with abilities first since this is
arguably the most important part aside
from choosing your subclass
your primary ability as a fighter is
strength or dexterity depending on how
you want to play your fighter strength
if you want to use heavy armor or a
two-handed weapon or maybe even a
one-handed Shield you might go dexterity
if you prefer two weapon fighting though
you could still do this as a strength
fighter as well or if you prefer a
medium or light armor and like ranged
combat with a bow or crossbow
additionally Eldritch Knights may want
to take some intelligence to increase
their likelihood of them Landing hostile
spells and can trips so that is
something to consider as well
strength increases your melee hit chance
melee damage increases carry weight and
chance to shove someone successfully as
well as increases jump distance and
improves athletic checks and strength
saving throws
dexterity increases your hit chance with
finesse melee weapons and ranged weapons
damaging roles with these weapon types
boost armor class if not wearing heavy
armor increases initiative and improves
sleight of hand acrobatics and stealth
checks as well as improved dexterity
saving throws intelligence is useful to
Eldritch Knights who want their hostile
spells and cantrips to connect more
regularly it also boosts intelligent
skill checks and intelligence saving
throws but does not increase the number
of prepared spells Eldritch Knights have
since they don't need to prepare their
spells like Wizards do
Constitution is there to help keep you
alive via HP since Fighters typically
soak up a lot of damage when on the
front lines
your stat spread for your fighter will
vary depending on which route you want
to go but you'll likely want 16 strength
or 16 dexterity and at least 14
Constitution
you can see the following setups on the
screen for a fighter to help you better
set up for the type you want to play
note I've changed this from the
recommendations as it's more optimized
for your character during the early
goings of the game also note that you
can play a dexterity focused Elder
tonight if you wish instead of strength
and then if you plan to only use Buffs
or just like magic Missile on your
Eldritch Knight then you really don't
need intelligence
when it comes to what race to select
Fighters have all proficiencies and
weapons and armor and shields so
choosing a race will come down to what
else they can bring to the table since
those are not needed for instance drow
have Superior dark vision Fey ancestry
and perception proficiency which are all
decent pickups for the fighter goldwarf
is also not a bad choice for dark vision
Dwarven resilience and Dwarven toughness
though they have lower movement speed
which isn't ideal for Fighters
half orc is also a good choice
especially for melee focused Fighters
since they have dark vision Relentless
endurance Savage attacks and menacing
for skills what you select will not have
a huge impact in the game Fighters
typically don't handle the dialogue of
their group though they can use
intimidation quite well compared to some
classes
Athletics is good to pick up for shoving
and helping to resist being shoved but
beyond that the choice of what skills
you want is really up to you
next let's take a look at General
Fighter character progression
at level 1 Fighters gain Second Wind
allowing them to heal themselves for one
d10 plus their fighter level of HP as a
bonus action once per short rest this is
a great way to help keep their HP up
during fights and still attack on the
same turn
also at this level all fighters can
choose one of six fighting styles
present in bg3 Fighters are the only
class that can choose from all six while
other classes can choose from A reduced
pool of fighting styles
at level 2 all fighters gain action
surge allowing them to take a second
action on their turn once every short
rest and as I mentioned before this
allows them to attack again which will
re-trigger extra attack once they've
acquired it allowing them to potentially
attack four times at level 5 and 6 times
at level 11 on a single turn this is an
extremely powerful class feature
at level 3 fighters choose a subclass
and gain subclass features based on the
subclass chosen we'll go into what these
are more in the subclasses section of
this guide
at level 4 Fighters will gain their
first feat ability Improvement is good
here for more strength or dexterity but
there are a ton of other Feats Fighters
can benefit from
dual wielder is great if you want to use
two rapiers and gain plus one Armor
class lucky is great for picking up some
uses of advantage and controlling
outcomes and Sharpshooter is great for
boosting range damage if you like
playing your fighter primarily from
ranged great weapon fighter is good in
general and even better if you're using
a two-handed weapon
Sentinel is not a bad pickup if you want
to stop enemies from moving if you hit
them with an attack of opportunity
and pull arm Master is great if you
intend to use one of these weapon types
at level 5 all fighters gain extra
attack allowing them to attack again on
their turn but only if they've used
their action to make an attack if you
use action surge this will allow you to
attack once again as an action
re-triggering this effect
at level 6 Fighters gain an extra feat
that no other class gets besides Rogues
though Rogues get this at level 10
instead of level 6.
and once again there are many good
choices here as I mentioned before and
because Fighters can reach 20 and their
main ability with ability Improvement
and still have two Feats left over they
have a lot of freedom to choose
at level 7 all fighters gain a subclass
feature based on the subclass they chose
at level 3. we'll cover these more in
the subclasses section
at level 8 all fighters gain another
feed and they can choose from any I
mentioned before though investing summon
strength or dexterity would be wise if
you have not done so already depending
on what your main stat is
at level 9 Fighters gain indomitable
allowing them to roll again once if they
fail to saving throw this drastically
improves their chances of passing saving
throws and can help protect them against
spells and other negative effects at
level 10 all fighters gain their final
subclass feature which again I will be
covering in our subclasses section at
level 11 Fighters gain improved extra
attack which allows him to make two
additional attacks if they use their
action to make an attack they are the
only class in vg3 that can do this as
most other Marshall classes only gain a
single extra attack and as I mentioned
before if they use action surge then
they can make two additional attacks a
second time for a total of six attacks
in one turn at level 12 all fighters
gain their final feat and they can
choose from any I mentioned before
though they should ideally max out their
main stat if they haven't already
fighter equipment will vary greatly from
fighter to fighter since they can go
many different directions however
strength Fighters will typically wear
heavy armor to allow them to invest
heavily into strength and Constitution
without sacrificing Armor class they can
still use medium if they wish and may do
so if they have 14 or so dexterity
dexterity-based fighters on the other
hand will likely use medium or light
armor to take advantage of their higher
dexterity though they have the option to
use heavy armor if they need it weapon
wise strength Fighters will either use a
two-handed weapon go one-handed inner
Shield or may even dual wield 2 weapons
if they want remember that finesse
weapons use strength or dexterity
whichever is higher they will also
likely throw weapons to deal damage at
range instead of using a lower crossbow
particularly if they have lower
dexterity while dexterity Fighters will
use a one-handed finesse weapon and
Shield or typically dual wield finesse
weapons in melee combat while using a
bow or crossbow at range
next let's take a look at subclasses
fighters in bg3 can play completely
differently based on their equipment and
fighting style alone but their
subclasses also dictate how they behave
in combat for instance Battle Masters
have many different actions they can use
that can add effects to their attacks
and they have a lot of freedom to choose
the ones they like
Champions on the other hand have a
higher critical hit chance allowing them
to land criticals more often they also
gain a second fighting style allowing
them to further specialize in combat
and Eldritch Knights can cast spells
both defensive and offensively allowing
them to augment their attacks with magic
that Fighters would not otherwise gain
all of these things together make
Fighters a very flexible class and it's
unlikely that any two fighters will be
exactly the same
all fighters gain their first subclass
feature at level 3 when they select
their subclass and then once again at
level 7 and finally one more time at
level 10. these features are not the
only thing that separates these
subclasses however since Eldritch
Knights also gained spell casting while
Battle Masters and champions do not
let's take a look at Battle Master first
at level 3 Battle Masters gain four
superiority dice that can be spent on
maneuvers they've selected
they will spend one superiority die per
maneuver used and these dice replenish
every short rest
at level 3 Battle Masters will also get
to select three Maneuvers from a list
each with their own benefits they will
use their security dice to use these and
this dice also adds 1d8 to damage in
many cases making these attacks even
stronger than default attacks from a
damage perspective
at level 7 they'll gain one more
superiority die they can use between
short rests giving them a total of five
dice which is the highest number of dice
they will obtain
and also level 7 Battle Masters will
gain two more Maneuvers from the list
that they can spend their superiority
dice on
and finally at level 10 Battle Masters
will gain two more Maneuvers from the
list and their security dice will
increase from d8 to d10 adding more
damage to Maneuvers that use them
next let's take a look at champion
at level 3 Champions will gain improved
critical hit which allows them to
critically hit when rolling a 19 or 20
instead of just 20 on their attack roll
this effectively doubles their crit
chance which is roughly a five percent
increase up to 10 percent
note that this effect can stack with
other effects that reduce the number
needed on the die when making an attack
rule to critically hit which can add up
when set up properly
at level 7 Champions can jump 3 meters
further than other Fighters and can add
half their proficiency bonus to any
strength dexterity or Constitution
checks they make that they aren't
proficient with
and at level 10 Champions gain a second
fighting style making them the only
fighter that has access to two different
ones without multi-classing
and lastly we come to Eldritch Knight at
level 3 Eldritch Knights gain the
capability to cast spells in and outside
of combat this sets them apart from the
other subclasses since neither of them
can do this they use intelligence for
their spell casting ability modifier
just like Wizards and arcane tricksters
and also a level 3 Elder tonight's also
gain weapon bond preventing their weapon
from being knocked out of their hand by
disarming attacks and this feature also
allows them to throw their weapon and
have it return to them automatically
which is great if you like to throw your
weapon at level 7 Eldritch Knights
gained War magic which allows them to
cast a can trip with their action and
then attack with their weapon as a bonus
action in the same turn
this can be useful but remember that
Eldritch Knights also have extra attack
and they cannot attack twice if they
cast a cantrip with their action
and finally at level 10 Eldritch Knights
inflict disadvantage on saving throws
made to their next spell cast before the
end of their next turn against enemies
they hit with a weapon attack
this allows them to attack one turn and
then cast spells more effectively on the
next
in this section of revolvers Gate 3
fighter class guide we'll take a look at
multi-classing a fighter and what other
classes you might multi-class with keep
in mind this is not a complete list but
rather helpful suggestions that make
good pairings Fighters are heavily front
loaded meaning they gain a fighting
style at level 1 action surge at level 2
and they gain a lot from their subclass
features at level 3. this means the
first most likely place you would
multi-class the fighter would be after
this point at level 3. from this point
onward it's a lot less cut and drive out
when you should multi-class since it
really depends on what you need out of
your fighter and what subclass you chose
Fighters gain extra attack at level 5 so
if you made it to level 3 there is
definitely a case for making it to level
five and if you made it to level five
level six gives you another feat so
there's also a case to be made there as
well from this point onward however the
further you go in Fighter the less
likely you are to multi-class when
multi-classing Battle Master I like nine
levels of Battle Master and three of
thief if you plan to do a wield this
allows you to attack with your main and
offhands two times each per turn gives
you the option to Dash or disengage as a
bonus action and also provides you some
sneak attack damage
when multiclassing a champion I like
three levels of champion and nine levels
of Barbarian this is because you gain
access to rage further boosting your
melee damage and providing damage
resistance while only having to
sacrifice heavy armor to use rage you
also gain Reckless attack allowing you
to attack with Advantage every turn
which pairs nicely with the Champion's
chance to critically hit additionally a
level 9 barbarians gained brutal
critical allowing them to roll an
additional damage tie when they crit
making this even more deadly
when multi-classing Eldritch Knight I
like 10 levels of Eldritch Knight and
two of wizard in order to gain access to
level 3 spell slots and to be able to
learn spells from Scrolls as well as
pick up a wizard subclass feature like
Arcane War
this also allows the Eldritch Knight to
pick up all subclass features making it
especially potent
well that wraps up our fighter class
guide and I hope you were able to learn
something about fighters in this video
they are an extremely Dynamic class but
I feel like will be played much
differently from person to person even
if they chose the same subclass
and as always if you have further tips
about the fighter that I forgot to
mention please leave them in the
comments and if you have questions ask
them there as well and I will try and
answer them as soon as I can
[Music]
thank you